Hi and welcome to Learn WordPress, part<br />two of migrating your website to a new
hosting account. In part one, you<br />learned how to migrate your WordPress
website to a new hosting provider while<br />setting up a new domain name. In this
session, we'll be learning about the<br />different steps needed to complete the
website migration while keeping the<br />website's existing domain name.
By the end of this session, you should<br />be able to describe the steps necessary
to move your website to a new hosting<br />company when you want to continue to use
your existing domain name. Describe how<br />the internet knows where to look for
your website. And describe the steps<br />necessary to update the location of your
website so that visitors arrive at the<br />version of your site that is in your new
hosting location.
Migrating your WordPress website to a<br />new hosting company and keeping your
existing domain name is very similar to<br />migrating to a new hosting provider and
establishing a new domain name. When<br />keeping your current domain name, there
is a different selection you must make<br />at the beginning of the process, and one
additional step at the end of the<br />migration process.
When you establish a hosting account<br />with a new company, one of the first
questions that you will be asked in the<br />setup process is whether you are
establishing a new domain or whether you<br />already have an existing registered
domain name. If you already have a<br />domain name and wish to keep using it
you just check that option and enter<br />your existing domain name into the
appropriate box.
The new hosting company will then set up<br />your hosting account with that entry as
the primary domain will also provide you<br />with the information necessary to sign
into your hosting account and will<br />provide you with a temporary website
address to access the website that you<br />set up in the new account. Logging into
your new hosting account will allow you<br />to install WordPress. And the temporary
website address will allow you to access<br />your new WordPress Dashboard.
Once you have accessed your new<br />WordPress installation, you can
duplicate your current website in this<br />new hosting account using the same
process that you learned in part one of<br />migrating your WordPress website.
Basically, you install your preferred<br />migration plugin in this new website and
then use that plugin to import the file<br />on your computer that you downloaded
when you exported your website in its<br />old location. When that import is
completed, you will have duplicated your<br />existing website and your new hosting
account.
You now have your website located in two<br />places on the internet, in your old
hosting account and then your new one.<br />However, the internet only knows about
your old hosting account. Telling the<br />internet that your website is in a new
location is the extra step that you must<br />accomplish in the migration process.
Website addresses are actually a series<br />of numbers or numbers and letters called
an Internet Protocol address, or IP<br />address. These are examples of IP
addresses using versions four and six of<br />the numbering protocol. The domain names
that we use in our browsers like cnn.com<br />or espn.com are human readable names
that are paired to a specific numeric or<br />alphanumeric IP address that is part of
the internet's Domain Name System or<br />DNS.
When you type a domain address into your<br />browser, your request to go to that
location first checks with the domain<br />name system through Nameservers to look
up the numeric IP address associated<br />with the human readable address that you
said you want it to visit.
Your website in the new hosting account<br />has a different IP address from the one
in your old hosting account. Until you<br />update the information in the DNS or
Nameserver system. The Internet still<br />thinks your website is at its old
address.
You update your website's location by<br />changing the Nameserver settings of your
domain. These settings are located in<br />the account where you registered your
domain. If you registered your domain at<br />the same time that you established your
old hosting account, then that hosting<br />provider most likely is your domain
registrar. Most hosting providers are<br />also domain registrars and offer bundled
services as were described in the<br />previous lesson. Remember hosting and
domain registration are two separate<br />functions, even though you may have
initially set up both with the same<br />company at the same time.
When you established your new hosting<br />account, your hosting provider sent you
several pieces of information. One of<br />those pieces of information is the
Nameserver settings of your new account.<br />If you do not have that information
handy, you can log into your new hosting<br />account and find it in the area where
you manage your domain settings. They'll<br />look something like this. There are
usually two of them.
You then take the new hosting account<br />Nameservers settings, access your domain
registration account. Insert these new<br />Nameserver settings in place of the old
ones and save the change.
The length of time it will take for this<br />change to propagate through the internet
can vary. Typically it takes 24 to 48<br />hours a law in some cases, it may take
up to 72 hours.
If you have made your website in this<br />new hosting account identical to the
site in the old hosting account it may<br />be difficult to notice when the
Nameserver changes become effective. One<br />trick you can use is to make a small
wording or style change to the website<br />located in the new hosting account. Then
in a day or two, navigate to the website<br />using your domain name. If you see that
change on the page you will know that<br />you have successfully completed the
migration and you're looking at the<br />website and your new hosting account.
Congratulations!
There are a few other things to consider<br />about your website migration.
One is email accounts. The email<br />addresses associated with your domain
are part of your hosting account. When<br />you change hosting companies, you'll
have to set up those email addresses in<br />your new hosting account. Some hosting
companies will migrate all of your email<br />accounts for you when you set up a new
account.
If you added or updated content on your<br />live website, after you made that
website migration export file, those<br />changes will not appear in your new
website. The exported website file was a<br />snapshot of your site when it was made.
Any more recent changes to the site will<br />have to be manually duplicated in your
new site.
Remember that you now have service rules<br />from two companies. Your domain
registration will be handled by the<br />company where it is registered. And
using the example above that will be<br />your old hosting company. You will also
have a hosting account renewal with your<br />new hosting company.
The process of changing name server<br />settings or changing domain registrar's
varies between companies. It's best to<br />look through the help or support
sections of your hosting account to find<br />the specific steps to take in your
situation. I hope you've enjoyed<br />learning just a little bit more about
website migrations. Join us again on<br />Learn WordPress and continue WordPress
learning journey.